<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Signal Fires PDX</title>
    <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com" />
    <updated>2025-09-30T11:46:47-07:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Signal Fire</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://signalfirespdx.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>The Land of the Free is Smaller than I Thought</title>
        <author>
            <name>Signal Fire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/the-land-of-the-free-is-smaller-than-i-realized/"/>
        <id>https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/the-land-of-the-free-is-smaller-than-i-realized/</id>
        <media:content url="https://signalfirespdx.com/media/posts/9/bafkreidrqreqi7igjbibmcgwwplzmihypo4iekbbqyodacn3i7o34a4gvi-2.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-09-29T17:08:02-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://signalfirespdx.com/media/posts/9/bafkreidrqreqi7igjbibmcgwwplzmihypo4iekbbqyodacn3i7o34a4gvi-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    When 9/11 happened, I was still in elementary school. Even then, I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://signalfirespdx.com/media/posts/9/bafkreidrqreqi7igjbibmcgwwplzmihypo4iekbbqyodacn3i7o34a4gvi-2.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>When 9/11 happened, I was still in elementary school. Even then, I could tell that the Patriot Act was a terrible idea. I knew it gave the government sweeping powers, but I didn’t realize just how much of the country it actually covers until recently.</p><p>I knew about PRISM, the secret NSA program Edward Snowden exposed in 2013, where the government was tapping into Verizon call records and siphoning data straight from companies like Google, Apple, Facebook, and Microsoft. That alone felt like a betrayal: proof that “national security” could be used as an excuse to watch all of us online, all the time.</p><p>But what I didn’t realize was how much the same laws bleed into our <em>physical lives</em> too.  Checkpoints, patrols, and the very real threat of ICE showing up with the power to detain or deport without a judge.</p><p>I started digging into ICE because of everything happening now. What I found floored me: there’s something called the <strong>“100-mile border zone.”</strong> By law, ICE and Border Patrol get special powers inside this band, stretching 100 miles from any border or coastline. Courts also treat international airports as if they were borders, so every airport has its own 100-mile radius too.</p><hr>
<h2 id="when-i-mapped-it-out">When I Mapped it Out</h2>
<p> I realized: I’ve lived almost my whole life inside these zones without knowing it. Most Americans have.</p><p>On the map you’ll see:</p><ul>
<li>🟠 <strong>Orange circles</strong> = 25 miles, where agents can even patrol private land (not homes).</li>
<li>🟢 <strong>Green shading</strong> = 100 miles around airports.</li>
<li>🔵 <strong>Blue circles</strong> = 100 miles from the land borders.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="the-constitution-free-zone">The Constitution-Free Zone</h2>
<p>Inside these areas, ICE/CBP can:</p><ul>
<li>Stop and question you at checkpoints without suspicion.</li>
<li>Board buses, trains, and cars without warrants.</li>
<li>Deport non-citizens without a judge if they can’t prove two years here.</li>
<li>Search your bags or phone at airports like you never left customs.</li>
</ul>
<p>Even U.S. citizens are not immune. People have been detained or even wrongfully deported when they could not immediately prove their status.</p><p>Constitutional protections do not vanish here, but they bend. Full rights only remain in the unshaded parts of the map: the prairies between the zones, the pockets of liberty outside the 100-mile radius. And for most of us, those spaces are smaller than we ever imagined.</p><p>As Benjamin Franklin warned long before the Patriot Act:  </p><blockquote>
<p>“Those who would give up essential Liberty, to purchase a little temporary Safety, deserve neither Liberty nor Safety.”
 <cite>&mdash; Benjamin Franklin</cite></p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="are-we-really-free">Are We Really Free?</h2>
<p>I grew up hearing “land of the free.” But when two-thirds of us live inside this border zone, the freedoms I thought were guaranteed suddenly look a lot smaller.</p><p>Check out the map below: are you free, or are you like most of us, standing where the color touches?</p><p>Are we really free when so much of the country is treated like a checkpoint?</p><div class="post__iframe"><iframe loading="lazy" allowfullscreen style='position: static; height: 40lvh; border-radius: 1rem;' src='/media/files/patriot-act-border/'></iframe></div>

<ul>
<li>🟠 <strong>Orange circles</strong> = 25 miles, where agents can even patrol private land (not homes).</li>
<li>🟢 <strong>Green shading</strong> = 100 miles around airports.</li>
<li>🔵 <strong>Blue circles</strong> = 100 miles from the land borders.</li>
</ul>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Victory! Portland Issues Land Use Violation to ICE Facility</title>
        <author>
            <name>Revoke The Ice Permit</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/victory-portland-issues-land-use-violation-to-ice-facility/"/>
        <id>https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/victory-portland-issues-land-use-violation-to-ice-facility/</id>
        <media:content url="https://signalfirespdx.com/media/posts/10/victory1-2.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-09-18T11:39:00-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://signalfirespdx.com/media/posts/10/victory1-2.jpg" alt="" />
                    One step closer to shutting down the South Waterfront facility. On September&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://signalfirespdx.com/media/posts/10/victory1-2.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>One step closer to shutting down the South Waterfront facility.</p><hr>
<p>On September 18, 2025, the City of Portland issued a <strong>land use violation notice</strong> to the ICE Facility on Macadam. This comes after years of permit violations — both in how ICE treats immigrants and in how it endangers the surrounding neighborhood — and years of relentless community organizing to shut the facility down.</p><p>This is a victory! Portland city government is finally standing up to ICE. But make no mistake: this win belongs to <em>the people</em>, not those in power.</p><p>It belongs to:</p><p>✊🏽 The protestors at Macadam every single day</p><p>✊🏽 The petition creators and every person who signed and shared</p><p>✊🏽 Those who joined protests across the city to hold officials accountable</p><p>✊🏽 The residents who filed complaints with the City</p><p>✊🏽 Everyone who has taken action to revoke this permit</p><p>What this shows us is clear: we can’t let up the pressure. <strong>We can’t slow down!</strong> It was only after disruptions of city council meetings and direct confrontations with the mayor that any action was taken. Now that the notice has been issued, politicians will tell us to slow down and “let the process play out.” We reject that. This is the moment to <strong>turn up the pressure even more.</strong></p><p>Here’s what comes next:</p><p>➡️ After 60 days, David Kuhnhausen, Director of Permitting and Development, can begin the reconsideration process — regardless of ICE’s attempts to “rectify” the violation. We demand he act the moment that window opens.</p><p>➡️ We also demand that City Council and the Mayor act even sooner. The decision cannot rest in the hands of one person while this facility continues to operate and abuse our communities every day.</p><p>This is just one step in the fight for justice for immigrants and to get ICE out of Portland. We will not stop until the Macadam facility is gone and ICE is out of our city.</p><p>#RevokeThePermit #ICEOutOfPDX #PowerToThePeople</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Open Letter: Let’s Not Divide the Movement Over the ICE Building Closure</title>
        <author>
            <name>Signal Fire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/open-letter-lets-not-divide-the-movement-over-the-ice-building-closure/"/>
        <id>https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/open-letter-lets-not-divide-the-movement-over-the-ice-building-closure/</id>

        <updated>2025-06-25T16:24:07-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Protestors, legal advocates, and immigrant communities are fighting the same system. Let’s&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><strong>Protestors, legal advocates, and immigrant communities are fighting the same system. Let’s stay focused.</strong></p><blockquote>
<p>This letter comes from local protestors and community members who have been present outside the Portland ICE facility. We wrote it to clarify the impact of the building’s closure, push back against division, and call for deeper unity in the fight for immigrant justice.</p></blockquote>
<p>In recent weeks, Portland’s ICE field office has been closed to the public, and it has made a difficult situation worse for many immigrants. Legal advocates and families have raised serious concerns, and they’re right to do so. When people are detained and transferred out of state without access to legal help, it’s a crisis.</p><p>But let’s be clear about who made that happen.</p><p>The decision to close the Portland ICE building was made by federal authorities. Protestors didn’t shut the doors. ICE and DHS did. To imply otherwise, or to omit this critical context, is not just misleading. It risks fracturing a movement that is already under pressure.</p><p>Many of us protesting outside that building are doing so in direct solidarity with immigrants, not in opposition to them. We are there because we want the detentions to stop. Because we want to bear witness. Because we want a future without ICE.</p><p>Yes, the closure of the building has removed one of the last local intervention points where lawyers could act quickly. But that was already a fragile system, not a just one. The solution isn’t to preserve ICE facilities in the name of access. It’s to build new forms of community-based legal infrastructure while we continue to dismantle the system that detains and deports our neighbors.</p><p>We believe legal advocates, protestors, and immigrant organizers should be working together, not being pitted against each other by narratives that ignore how this system actually works.</p><p>So we’re calling on:</p><ul>
<li>Media outlets to include the voices of protestors in coverage, especially when describing cause and effect</li>
<li>Legal organizations to open lines of communication with those witnessing outside detention sites</li>
<li>Community members to resist the temptation to blame each other when it’s the system that deserves the scrutiny</li>
</ul>
<p>We can hold multiple truths at once. We can grieve the harm this closure causes and still demand abolition. We can fight for better legal access and still protest ICE’s existence. We can show up differently, but toward the same goal.</p><p>Let’s not let omission divide us. Let’s stay focused. Let’s keep building and dismantling together.</p><p><strong>Signed by</strong>
Local advocates for immigrant rights and protest safety
(and others in solidarity — contact us to co-sign)</p><p>If this letter resonates with you as a protestor, advocate, or community member, we invite you to co-sign and share.</p><p>To add your name, email <a href="mailto:&#115;&#105;&#x67;&#110;&#x61;&#x6c;&#102;&#x69;&#x72;&#x65;&#115;&#112;&#100;&#x78;&#64;&#112;&#114;&#111;&#x74;&#111;&#x6e;&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;">&#115;&#105;&#x67;&#110;&#x61;&#x6c;&#102;&#x69;&#x72;&#x65;&#115;&#112;&#100;&#x78;&#64;&#112;&#114;&#111;&#x74;&#111;&#x6e;&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;</a>
To help spread the message, share this letter with your networks, especially in spaces where there is confusion or division around the ICE building closure.</p><p>We show up in different ways, but we are in this together. Let’s keep our focus on the system, not each other.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Collapsing Shield</title>
        <author>
            <name>Signal Fire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/the-collapsing-shield/"/>
        <id>https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/the-collapsing-shield/</id>

        <updated>2025-06-21T03:08:02-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    It’s scary to watch antisemitism rise again. It’s natural to want strong&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>It’s scary to watch antisemitism rise again.
It’s natural to want strong defenders, people who will speak up for Jewish safety.
And right now, many of those voices are coming from the political right.</p><hr>
<p><strong>But we need to be honest about what kind of protection this is.</strong></p><p>For many Jewish people in America, this support feels reassuring.
After centuries of displacement, persecution, and genocide, any promise of strong allies feels like safety.
The fear is real. The history is real.</p><p>But we have to look at who is offering this protection and why.</p><p>Much of this “support” isn’t coming from people who care about long-term Jewish safety.
It’s coming from powerful conservative religious movements that see Israel as part of their political and religious agenda: a symbol tied to their own vision of power, destiny, and control.</p><p>These are some of the same Christian movements that once drove Jews out of Israel centuries ago,
that helped spark conflict between Jews and Muslims,
and that now believe the Jewish return to Israel is a necessary step to trigger an apocalyptic prophecy —
a prophecy where Jews are ultimately either converted or destroyed to bring Jesus back.</p><p>At the same time, far-right nationalists seize the opportunity to wrap themselves in “defending Israel”
while attacking immigrants,
banning black history,
stripping civil rights from queer people,
and fueling white nationalist movements that have never abandoned their antisemitism.</p><p><strong>They chant <em>“Jews will not replace us”</em> on Saturday,
and pledge support for Israel on Sunday.</strong></p><p><strong>It’s not protection.
It’s a tool shaped for an end.
And that end has never been Jewish safety.</strong></p><hr>
<h2 id="this-isnt-happening-by-accident">This isn’t happening by accident.</h2>
<p><strong>Project Esther, created by The Heritage Foundation, has been built to engineer what we can call conversation collapse.</strong></p><p>Every criticism of Israeli policy becomes framed as antisemitism.
Any concern for Palestinian human rights is treated as a threat to Jewish safety.
Hard conversations are shut down before they can even happen.</p><p><strong>This is the machinery of conversation collapse:</strong></p><ul>
<li>The space where accountability should happen disappears.</li>
<li>The space where Jewish safety and universal human rights could coexist disappears.</li>
<li>The only choices left become blind loyalty or dangerous conspiracy.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>And every time the conversation collapses further, the extremes grow stronger.</strong></p><hr>
<p><strong>The Israeli government takes full advantage of this conversation collapse.</strong></p><p>Any time someone raises concerns about:</p><ul>
<li>The bombings,</li>
<li>The settlements,</li>
<li>The occupation,</li>
<li>The walls,</li>
<li>The daily dehumanization of Palestinians.</li>
</ul>
<p>it’s instantly framed as antisemitism.</p><p><strong>Real accountability disappears.</strong></p><p>The government moves forward without limits.
The conversation gets shut down.
Solidarity fractures.
Movements divide.</p><hr>
<p><strong>And all the while, the real danger grows.</strong></p><p>The far right gains power.
Antisemitism festers beneath the surface, waiting for its opening.
The shield weakens.</p><hr>
<h2 id="this-collapsing-shield-doesnt-protect-jewish-people">This collapsing shield doesn’t protect Jewish people.</h2>
<p>It isolates them.
It leaves them dependent on alliances with people who have always targeted minorities, putting everyone’s long-term safety at risk.**</p><hr>
<p><strong>If we want real safety, we need to stop collapsing every criticism into an attack on our existence.</strong></p><ul>
<li>We need to hold governments accountable, even Israel.</li>
<li>We need to defend human dignity for everyone. Not just for those who hold power now.</li>
<li>We need the courage to stay in the uncomfortable middle, where real safety is built.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="we-dont-have-to-stay-on-this-path"><strong>We don’t have to stay on this path.</strong></h2>
<p>We can hold governments accountable without feeding hatred.
We can defend Jewish safety without silencing others.
We can reject being used as tools in someone else’s agenda.</p><p><strong>But only if we refuse to let fear keep collapsing the conversation.</strong></p><p>The only way forward is together.
When we stand up for <em>everyone’s</em> dignity, we build the kind of safety no authoritarian movement can ever take from any us.</p><p>We don’t need stronger walls.
We need stronger solidarity.
Because that’s the only real shield that works.</p><hr>
<h3 id="definition-conversation-collapse"><strong>Definition: Conversation Collapse</strong></h3>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Conversation collapse</strong> refers to the breakdown of meaningful discussion when any criticism or inquiry into harm, injustice, or abuse is immediately reframed as an attack on identity, safety, or existence itself.</p><p>As the conversation collapses, space for accountability disappears.
One side hardens into unconditional defense, rejecting any discussion of harm.
The other drifts into radicalized hostility, collapsing policies into identity and fueling new forms of bigotry.</p><p>In the vacuum, both extremes grow stronger while the underlying harms continue unchecked.</p></blockquote>
<p><em>Term introduced by Signal Fires, 2025.</em></p><hr>
<h3 id="reference-notes"><strong>Reference Notes</strong></h3>
<ol>
<li><p><strong>Crusader-era Christian persecution of Jews</strong></p><p> During the Crusades, many Jewish communities in Europe were massacred or expelled by Christian crusaders on their way to the Holy Land (<a href="https://jewishinsider.com/2024/10/heritage-foundation-project-esther-combat-antisemitism/">Jewish Insider</a>, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/ng-interactive/2025/mar/23/antisemitism-redefinition-jewish-safety-christian-nationalism-democracy">The Guardian</a>, <a href="https://www.haaretz.com/opinion/2025-03-09/ty-article-opinion/.premium/why-is-netanyahus-israel-cozying-up-to-europes-antisemitic-far-right/00000195-6b44-d55d-a39f-ff7eecb70000">Haaretz</a>, <a href="https://historyguild.org/the-crusades/?srsltid=AfmBOoqhJhkL5Bi_TB1KEPyP16FJMBMIoeml2I2s8bUsRCcqCWhKOoYm&utm_source=chatgpt.com">History Guild</a>).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Christian theological roots fueling conflict</strong></p><p> Early Christian leaders, including Justin Martyr, Melito of Sardis, and Augustine, taught that the Christian church had replaced the Jewish people as God’s chosen. This doctrine, known as <strong>supersessionism</strong> (or <em>replacement theology</em>), fueled centuries of antisemitism, laying the groundwork for systemic persecution and interfaith conflict that persists to this day. (<a href="https://lifeinmessiah.org/articles/history-of-christian-antisemitism">Life in Messiah - “Overview of the History of Christian Antisemitism”</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supersessionism">Wikipedia — Supersessionism</a>)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Project Esther as modern instrument</strong></p><p> Heritage Foundation’s Project Esther strategy actively characterizes criticism of Israel as antisemitism, while ignoring white nationalist antisemitism — criticized by outlets including Al Jazeera, The Forward, and Vox (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Esther">Wikipedia</a>).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Israeli government exploiting conversation collapse</strong></p><p> Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and other officials have repeatedly labeled international criticism, including from the ICC, UN, and Human Rights Watch, as “antisemitic.” This framing is used to shut down debate and deflect accountability for actions like settlement expansion and civilian harm. It takes full advantage of the dynamics of conversation collapse. (<a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/world/netanyahu-frequently-makes-claims-of-antisemitism-critics-say-hes-deflecting-blame">PBS Newshour - “Not every criticism against Israel is antisemitic” - Israeli historian Tom Segev</a>, <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/world/netanyahu-accuses-icc-of-anti-semitism-in-pursuit-of-war-crimes-probe-idUSKBN1YR07Y/">Reuters - Netanyahu calls ICC probe “pure anti-Semitism”</a>)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Silencing criticism via the Livingstone Formulation</strong></p><p> This recognized tactic deflects genuine criticism of Israel by accusing the critic of bad faith antisemitism. Coined by sociologist David Hirsh and named after former London mayor Ken Livingstone, it describes how criticism is shut down not by addressing arguments, but by attacking the critic’s motives. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Livingstone_Formulation">Wikipedia — Livingstone Formulation</a>, <a href="https://research.gold.ac.uk/7144/1/hirsh_transversal_2010.pdf">Goldsmiths Research Repository (Hirsh 2010 original paper)</a>, <a href="https://engageonline.wordpress.com/2016/04/29/the-livingstone-formulation-david-hirsh-2/">Engage — Hirsh summary (archived blog post)</a>)</p></li>
</ol>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>I Wanted to Know Why People Did Nothing. Now I am seeing it</title>
        <author>
            <name>Signal Fire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/i-wanted-to-know/"/>
        <id>https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/i-wanted-to-know/</id>

        <updated>2025-06-20T12:44:39-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    When I was a child learning about World War II in school,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>When I was a child learning about World War II in school, one question haunted me more than any other:
<strong>How could people sit by and do nothing while it was happening?</strong></p><p>How could entire communities convince themselves to look away as families were deported, then murdered? How could so many people rationalize what they saw, while the machinery of cruelty slowly built itself?</p><p>Now, decades later, I’m seeing it first hand. And I finally understand how it happens.</p><hr>
<h2 id="the-early-stages-of-deportation-a-historical-pattern"><strong>The Early Stages of Deportation: A Historical Pattern</strong></h2>
<p>We tend to think of the Holocaust as a single, horrifying moment of extermination. But it unfolded in stages, over years. In 1939–1941, before the full industrial genocide began, Nazi policy focused on deporting Jews from Germany, Austria, and Czechoslovakia to <strong>occupied Poland</strong>. Families were rounded up and transported into ghettos in Warsaw, Lodz, and Lublin, often under the euphemism of “relocation.”</p><blockquote>
<p>“Concentrate and intern the Jews in separate neighborhoods in the cities, for reasons associated with general police security, while taking economic needs into account.”
— Reinhard Heydrich, September 21, 1939 (<a href="https://www.nationalww2museum.org/war/articles/nazi-germany-and-establishment-ghettos">National WWII Museum</a>)</p></blockquote>
<p>Reinhard Heydrich, the German SS and police official who issued this order, was a principal architect of the Holocaust. This directive came as deportations to occupied Poland began in 1939. Roughly a year before the genocide began. Even at this stage, the rationalizations were already being framed as public safety and economic necessity.</p><p>The rhetoric of “economic needs” echoes eerily into the present. Even now, many argue that immigrants and deportation targets should be sacrificed for the sake of resource scarcity, housing shortages, or protecting “our own people first.”</p><p>As one Portland resident recently argued online:</p><blockquote>
<p><em>“We simply cannot afford to pay for everything for everyone from everywhere. This country takes in enough people legally. There is no way newcomers just looking to take someone else’s share should get swanky hotels and get out of jail free passes while our own vets and citizens rot in the gutter.”</em></p></blockquote>
<p>The same justifications of protecting resources, managing housing availability, and prioritizing local citizens are again being used to rationalize deportations today, including the forced removal of U.S. citizens into foreign detention systems. The cruelty is repackaged as pragmatic policy, but the underlying logic remains the same. Some lives are treated as more disposable than others.</p><p>This normalization, the slow social acceptance of escalating cruelty, was the foundation upon which the later extermination machine was built.</p><hr>
<h2 id="what-we-are-seeing-today"><strong>What We Are Seeing Today</strong></h2>
<p>Here in the United States, we are witnessing families being deported into foreign detention systems, including U.S. citizens and children who have never lived in the countries they’re being sent to.</p><p>I’ve personally seen cases where children recovering from brain cancer were uprooted from the only home they’ve ever known. Families who lived here peacefully for decades are being torn apart. People who trusted in American legal processes are being suddenly vanished into foreign detention systems with no support structure waiting for them.</p><p>When confronted with these stories, many people instinctively pivot to argue about unrelated policies, technicalities, or bureaucratic language. It is easier to debate side issues than to sit with what is actually happening to our neighbors.</p><p>But looking away enables the harm.</p><hr>
<h2 id="the-danger-of-its-not-that-bad-yet"><strong>The Danger of “It’s Not That Bad Yet”</strong></h2>
<p>The most dangerous words in any society facing moral decline are some version of
<strong>“It’s not that bad yet.”</strong></p><p>Deporting families to foreign detention centers isn’t the end stage of an atrocity. It’s the part where ordinary people still have the chance to say <strong>no</strong> while they still can. History shows us that once cruelty becomes normalized and routine, escalation is easy.</p><p>Just as the Nazis pushed deportations into occupied territories to sidestep domestic scrutiny, we have developed legal structures that allow people to be sent into foreign detention systems where oversight is weaker and the public feels less directly responsible. Distance makes the cruelty easier to rationalize.</p><p><strong>This isn’t about what happens after full genocide begins.  It’s about how entire societies normalize the behavior that makes genocide possible later.</strong></p><p>I no longer wonder how people allowed it to happen in the 1940s. I see it unfolding right now. And I hope we have the courage to stop repeating that history.</p><hr>
<h2 id="further-historical-resources">Further Historical Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Bundesarchiv (German Federal Archives) — Warsaw Ghetto Uprising, April 1943</strong>
<a href="https://www.bundesarchiv.de/themen-entdecken/online-entdecken/geschichtsgalerien/19-april-1943-aufstand-im-warschauer-ghetto/">https://www.bundesarchiv.de/themen-entdecken/online-entdecken/geschichtsgalerien/19-april-1943-aufstand-im-warschauer-ghetto/</a></p></li>
<li><p><strong>United States Holocaust Memorial Encyclopedia — Deportations to and from the General Government</strong>
<a href="https://encyclopedia.ushmm.org/content/en/article/deportations-to-and-from-the-general-government">https://encyclopedia.ushmm.org/content/en/article/deportations-to-and-from-the-general-government</a></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Yad Vashem — Deportations during the Holocaust</strong>
<a href="https://www.yadvashem.org/holocaust/about/deportations.html">https://www.yadvashem.org/holocaust/about/deportations.html</a></p></li>
<li><p><strong>The National WWII Museum — Nazi Germany and the Establishment of Ghettos</strong>
<a href="https://www.nationalww2museum.org/war/articles/nazi-germany-and-establishment-ghettos">https://www.nationalww2museum.org/war/articles/nazi-germany-and-establishment-ghettos</a></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Wikipedia — History of the Jews in Poland: Ghettos and Death Camps</strong> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Jews_in_Poland#Ghettos_and_death_camps">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Jews_in_Poland#Ghettos_and_death_camps</a></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Gutman, Israel (1990). Encyclopedia of the Holocaust. Macmillan Publishing.</strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Gilbert, Martin (1986). The Holocaust: A History of the Jews of Europe During the Second World War. Henry Holt &amp; Co.</strong></p></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Signal Fires</strong> exists to help our neighbors face hard truths, organize around real civic action, and defend each other before it’s too late.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Hidden Cruelty of Progressive Cities: A Portland Case Study</title>
        <author>
            <name>Signal Fire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/the-hidden-cruelty-of-progressive-cities-a-portland-case-study/"/>
        <id>https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/the-hidden-cruelty-of-progressive-cities-a-portland-case-study/</id>

        <updated>2025-06-19T00:17:45-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    At first glance, Portland prides itself on being one of the most&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>At first glance, Portland prides itself on being one of the most progressive cities in America. Sanctuary city policies. Police reform initiatives. Climate action plans. Affordable housing goals. The national narrative paints Portland as a progressive beacon.</p><p>But when you look closer, the reality is much harder to swallow.</p><p>In many ways, <strong>Portland is <em>less</em> inclusive, and far more quietly brutal, than many of its conservative counterparts.</strong> Its exclusion is simply better camouflaged, wrapped in comforting rhetoric that allows residents to believe they’re on the right side of history.</p><hr>
<h2 id="zoning-the-machinery-of-gentle-exclusion">Zoning: The Machinery of Gentle Exclusion</h2>
<p>Portland’s single-family zoning system long served as a quiet tool of racial and class segregation, legally barring multi-family and affordable options from the majority of residential neighborhoods.</p><ul>
<li>Until 2020, <strong>70% of Portland’s residential land was reserved for single-family homes</strong>, locking out lower-income and racially diverse families from many neighborhoods.</li>
<li>The much-celebrated <strong>Residential Infill Project (RIP)</strong> modestly loosened these restrictions, but still faced aggressive opposition from neighborhood associations—many of whom framed their objections in terms of “preserving neighborhood character.”</li>
<li>Even with RIP, the permitting process remains so complicated and expensive that actual affordable multi-family development has been extremely limited. Between 2021-2023, duplexes and triplexes accounted for a tiny fraction of new housing units.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, <strong>wealthier enclaves like Eastmoreland and Laurelhurst remain effectively walled off</strong> through both zoning inertia and local resistance to change.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Progressive branding, exclusionary outcome.</em></p><hr>
<h2 id="sanctuary-city--but-only-on-paper">Sanctuary City — But Only on Paper</h2>
<p>Portland’s official designation as a <strong>sanctuary city</strong> masks the quiet complicity with federal enforcement activities operating within its borders.</p><ul>
<li>The <strong>ICE facility on Macadam Avenue</strong> operates under a city-issued conditional use permit. Despite years of community protests, gas exposure harming nearby schools like Cottonwood, and documented abuses, city officials have largely shrugged at their legal authority to revoke or modify the permit.</li>
<li>In 2020 and 2021, Portland police repeatedly coordinated with federal agents during protests. Protestors opposing ICE actions were tear-gassed, surveilled, and arrested—while city leaders claimed helplessness due to “federal jurisdiction.”</li>
<li>Publicly, officials declared support for immigrants. Privately, they <strong>protected ICE’s operational status</strong> and criminalized those attempting to resist.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Sanctuary in name, compliance in practice.</em></p><hr>
<h2 id="policing-reform-rhetoric-vs-reality">Policing: Reform Rhetoric vs. Reality</h2>
<p>After the 2020 uprisings, Portland politicians spoke at length about police reform and racial justice. But the outcomes tell a different story.</p><ul>
<li><strong>Qualified immunity remains intact</strong>; discipline for excessive force is rare.</li>
<li><strong>Portland Police Bureau’s (PPB) surveillance powers have been quietly rebuilt</strong>, including expanded use of body cams, license plate readers, and coordination with federal data sources.</li>
<li>In May 2021, leaked reports showed PPB engaged in <strong>misleading and aggressive tactics against protestors</strong>, including unlawful detentions and fabricated justifications for use of force.</li>
<li>Officers who fired “less-lethal munitions” on crowds at the ICE facility continue to serve with little consequence.</li>
</ul>
<p> <em>Progressive language shields regressive policing.</em></p><hr>
<h2 id="environmental-justice-delayed">Environmental Justice Delayed</h2>
<p>Portland’s environmental justice commitments often amount to <strong>endless process with minimal action</strong>.</p><ul>
<li>The <strong>Portland Harbor Superfund cleanup</strong> remains underfunded, slow, and weighted by corporate legal delays — despite clear evidence of disproportionate harm to communities of color along the Willamette.</li>
<li>North Portland neighborhoods impacted by <strong>diesel freight corridors and industrial pollution</strong> see higher rates of asthma and cancer risk — but meaningful regulatory action remains stalled behind task forces and “stakeholder dialogue.”</li>
<li>Residents have been documenting these health effects for over a decade, while city officials continue to host workshops rather than enforce stricter air quality standards.</li>
</ul>
<p> <em>Public health sacrificed to avoid conflict with industry donors.</em></p><hr>
<h2 id="homelessness-compassionate-language-cruel-policies">Homelessness: Compassionate Language, Cruel Policies</h2>
<p>Portland’s visible homelessness crisis exposes the gap between its compassionate rhetoric and its actual governance.</p><ul>
<li>The city’s <strong>camp sweeps displace vulnerable people almost weekly</strong>, often citing public safety concerns or neighborhood complaints.</li>
<li>In 2022, Portland established <strong>“Safe Rest Villages”</strong>—a modest alternative housing program that served only a fraction of the unhoused population while allowing large sweeps to continue.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, zoning restrictions, permitting delays, and developer cost concerns continue to suppress large-scale affordable housing construction.</li>
<li>The end result: <strong>public relations wins for city leaders</strong>, but little systemic relief for unhoused residents trapped in cycles of displacement.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="compassion-used-as-a-public-relations-shield-for-inaction----and-if-any-of-this-still-feels-abstract-look-at-what-portlands-leaders-did-just-this-month"> <em>Compassion used as a public relations shield for inaction.</em>
 
 <strong>And if any of this still feels abstract, look at what Portland’s leaders did just this month.</strong>
 </h2>
<h2 id="public-spectacle-vs-public-need-the-stadium-vs-kindergarten">Public Spectacle vs. Public Need: The Stadium vs. Kindergarten</h2>
<p>The most revealing moments are when leaders show us <strong>what they actually prioritize</strong>. Portland just offered one of the clearest examples yet.</p><p>On <strong>June 17, 2025</strong>, Oregon lawmakers swiftly approved up to <strong>$800 million in public bonds</strong> to help finance a proposed Major League Baseball stadium at South Waterfront. The bonds, structured around a “jock tax” on player salaries, were justified as risk-free and prestige-building, even though Portland has no MLB franchise committed (<a href="https://www.opb.org/article/2025/06/17/oregon-lawmakers-pass-dollar800-million-bill-for-portland-mlb-stadium/">source</a>).</p><p><strong>The very next day</strong>, Governor Tina Kotek warned that the state could not afford to continue expanding early education programs like <strong>Preschool for All</strong> and universal kindergarten, arguing that tax burdens were pushing high-earners out of the state and threatening long-term revenue stability (<a href="https://www.wweek.com/news/schools/2025/06/18/kotek-says-preschool-for-all-tax-imperiling-oregon-tax-base/">source</a>).</p><p>Consider the math:</p><ul>
<li><strong>Universal kindergarten for 50,000 children statewide</strong> would likely cost in the range of <strong>$900 million annually</strong>.</li>
<li>Even a <strong>scaled-down expansion serving just 20,000 children</strong> would cost approximately <strong>$370 million annually</strong> — less than half of what was instantly greenlit for the stadium.</li>
</ul>
<p>In short: <strong>a baseball stadium with no guaranteed team received nearly instant financial backing. Expanded early education, with decades of proven social and economic benefit, was declared “unaffordable.”</strong></p><hr>
<h3 id="what-this-pattern-reveals">What This Pattern Reveals</h3>
<p>This is the same exclusionary mechanism that defines much of Portland’s governance:</p><ul>
<li>Public money flows easily when it serves <strong>private prestige, donor interests, or real estate development.</strong></li>
<li>Programs that serve <strong>children, working families, or marginalized communities</strong> face endless debate about sustainability and “fiscal responsibility.”</li>
<li>Politicians talk about inclusion while quietly choosing to fund projects that benefit the privileged few.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The cruelty here is not accidental — it’s systemic. And worse, it’s carefully obscured beneath progressive rhetoric that allows many Portlanders to feel virtuous while injustice continues.</strong></p><h2 id="the-double-speak-of-power-portlands-uncomfortable-truth">The Double-Speak of Power: Portland’s Uncomfortable Truth</h2>
<p>While publicly performing their progressive values, Portland’s leaders quietly uphold policies that harm the very communities they claim to support. The exclusion is polite, procedural, and sanitized — but no less damaging than overt discrimination elsewhere.</p><p>True progressivism requires more than talking points. It demands a willingness to confront entrenched power, even when that power funds your campaigns or sits on your boards and commissions. Most are not ready for that fight.</p><p><strong>The slogans are easy. The hard part is noticing who benefits, and who gets left behind. Start paying attention. Start asking the uncomfortable questions. The systems count on you not looking too closely.</strong></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Deportation Machine Next Door: Why Portland Needs to Revoke ICE&#x27;s Permit</title>
        <author>
            <name>Signal Fire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/deportation-machine-next-door/"/>
        <id>https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/deportation-machine-next-door/</id>

        <updated>2025-06-18T14:26:59-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    A lot of Portlanders know about the protests. They’ve seen the smoke,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>A lot of Portlanders know about the protests. They’ve seen the smoke, read the headlines, and watched the footage. But what many still don’t realize is what happens inside that plain beige office building off Macadam, quietly sitting next to a K–8 school.</p><p>This is Portland’s field office for Immigration and Customs Enforcement, specifically its Enforcement and Removal Operations division. It’s where federal agents process the people they’ve arrested across Portland, often during early morning raids. Here, people are fingerprinted, interrogated, and handed over to the federal deportation system. From this office, ICE coordinates transfers to faraway detention centers like Tacoma and arranges flights to deport people out of the country entirely.</p><p>Governor Tina Kotek has defended the facility by stating that it isn’t a detention center. <del>Technically, that’s true.</del> <strong>However, the facility is explicitly defined as a detention center in its 2011 Conditional Use Permit.</strong> [Correction] There are no long-term holding cells here. But that framing hides the real function of the building. This is where people are processed into the deportation system. Agents conduct interrogations, issue removal orders, and coordinate transfers to distant detention centers and deportation flights. Families are still torn apart because of what happens inside these walls. Calling it “administrative” doesn’t make the harm any less real.</p><p>All of this is happening quietly in our city because we allow it.</p><p>The building doesn’t even belong to the federal government. It’s <strong>privately owned</strong> by a local company, <strong>4310 Building LLC</strong>, and leased to ICE through a contract with the U.S. General Services Administration. A private landlord profits by renting space for deportation operations inside Portland city limits.</p><p>The facility operates under a conditional use permit issued by Portland’s city government back in 2011. City Council still has the power to revoke that permit.</p><p>Many Portlanders are surprised to learn this. After all, we call ourselves a sanctuary city. But while we embrace that label, we’ve allowed a key hub of ICE’s deportation machine to operate right next to a K–8 school, The Cottonwood School of Civics and Science. Only a narrow bike path separates federal deportation operations from Portland kids playing at recess.</p><blockquote>
<p>This isn’t hypothetical harm. It’s happening right here.</p></blockquote>
<h2 id="so-much-violence">So much violence</h2>
<p>During recent ICE Out of Portland protests, federal officers deployed tear gas, pepper rounds, and other crowd-control munitions directly next to the school grounds. Swabs taken directly from the spent canisters were sent to a local lab for analysis. The lab confirmed the presence of HC gas, a military-grade chemical agent banned from use in war due to its long-term health risks, as documented in the video created by a local portlander below.</p><p>This isn’t the first time the school has been impacted. After returning to in-person classes following COVID closures in 2020, parents found spent tear gas canisters and rubber bullets scattered across their children’s playground, left behind from earlier federal crackdowns.</p><p>The harm extends beyond the schoolyard. Retired residents at nearby Mirabella had to modify their HVAC systems after toxic gas seeped indoors. A local nurse was shot in the eye with a “less-lethal” round fired by federal agents, a head-level shot that violates use-of-force guidelines. Many hoped these kinds of violent crackdowns wouldn’t happen here, but the infrastructure that enables them remains fully intact.</p><p>In some cases, protesters have been charged under <a href="../oregons-riot-law">Oregon’s outdated riot statute</a>, a law originally passed during the reactionary backlash to the Civil Rights and Vietnam War protests of the 1960s. That law gives broad discretion to police and federal agents to escalate peaceful gatherings into “unlawful assemblies,” triggering aggressive force. The same vague law that was used to justify crackdowns downtown has now been used repeatedly to target protests outside the ICE facility. Portlanders who show up peacefully are being criminalized for bearing witness.</p><blockquote>
<p>This isn’t just about immigrants. It’s about all of us.</p></blockquote>
<p>ICE has a long history of mistakenly deporting U.S. citizens due to paperwork errors, racial profiling, and bad information. Lives permanently upended because a federal bureaucracy made a mistake. The Portland office helps process the paperwork that makes those mistakes possible. This is not some faraway injustice. It is happening here.</p><p>As historian Adam Goodman documents in <a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691182155/the-deportation-machine">The Deportation Machine</a>, this kind of harm is not accidental; it’s the product of a system intentionally designed to spread enforcement across decentralized offices, paperwork pipelines, and private contractors, making accountability diffuse, while the human cost remains devastatingly concentrated.</p><p>Even elected officials are not immune. In both California and New York, Democratic lawmakers have been physically blocked, detained, or even tackled simply for trying to observe, ask questions, or advocate for their constituents during ICE enforcement actions. The message is clear: not even those we elect are safe from retaliation when they try to hold these operations accountable. As long as facilities like this remain embedded inside our cities, political violence isn’t hypothetical.  It’s part of the machinery.</p><h2 id="we-can-change-this">We can change this</h2>
<p>Other cities are already taking action. Portland can too.</p><p>Just last week, Glendale canceled its ICE contract. Newark is shutting down ICE operations due to permitting violations. These cities are drawing a line, not to end federal enforcement entirely, but to refuse complicity in an unjust system. Portland has that same legal authority. Revoking ICE’s conditional use permit wouldn’t make federal agents disappear, but it would make their operations here much harder.</p><p>A grassroots petition is already live, and it’s working.</p><p>As of today, nearly 12,000 Portlanders have signed the petition calling for City Council to revoke the permit. Political research shows it often only takes about 3.5% of a city’s population to create real pressure for policy change. In Portland, that’s around 21,000 signatures. We’re already more than halfway there.</p><p>This isn’t about left or right. It’s about what kind of city we want to live in. Do we allow a quiet deportation hub to operate in our neighborhoods, next to our schools? Or do we live up to the values of safety, fairness, and accountability we say we believe in?</p><blockquote>
<p>Portland can make a different choice. But <strong>only if we act.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>If you want to learn more, you can read the petition here: <a href="https://campaigns.organizefor.org/petitions/revoke-the-permit-for-the-ice-detention-facility-in-portland">Revoke ICE’s permit — Petition link</a>
And watch this short explainer made by local Portlanders: <a href="https://youtu.be/W5bUkmjep3A?si=iwpAowL3ORVqFVpH">Video explainer</a></p><p>Many of us have also stopped by the memorial growing outside the facility. Quietly reading the stories, placing flowers, and bearing witness. Every person who takes a moment to show up makes it harder to pretend this isn’t happening.</p><p>Solidarity makes Portland bloom.</p><h3 id="correction-july-2025">Correction (July 2025):</h3>
<p>An earlier version of this post referenced a statement by Governor Tina Kotek claiming the ICE facility at 4310 S Macadam Avenue was not a detention center. However, after reviewing the Conditional Use Permit (CUP) issued by the City of Portland in 2011, we now know this is incorrect. The CUP explicitly defines the facility as a <strong>detention facility</strong>, with specific operating conditions related to custody and security.</p><p>While officials may characterize the facility as “administrative,” its legal classification and operational purpose confirm it is, in fact, a detention center. We have updated the post to reflect this more accurate description.</p><p>We believe in transparency and will continue to correct the record as new information emerges.</p><p>you can view the conditional use permit here <a href="https://efiles.portlandoregon.gov/record/16222724/">https://efiles.portlandoregon.gov/record/16222724/</a></p><p>and the other relevant documents here <a href="https://efiles.portlandoregon.gov/Record?q=recAnyWord%3A11-124052&sortBy=recCreatedOn&pagesize=25">https://efiles.portlandoregon.gov/Record?q=recAnyWord%3A11-124052&amp;sortBy=recCreatedOn&amp;pagesize=25</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Oregon’s Riot Law was Designed to Suppress Protest</title>
        <author>
            <name>Signal Fire</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/oregons-riot-law/"/>
        <id>https://signalfirespdx.com/posts/oregons-riot-law/</id>

        <updated>2025-06-16T16:00:00-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Oregon’s current riot law was born in a period of major political&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Oregon’s current riot law was born in a period of major political upheaval. In the late 1960s and early 1970s, lawmakers across the country responded to the Civil Rights Movement and anti–Vietnam War protests by passing legislation that gave police broad authority to shut down demonstrations. Oregon was no exception.</p><p>More than 50 years later, that law remains on the books. It’s vague, overly broad, and prone to abuse.</p><h3 id="what-the-law-says">What the Law Says</h3>
<p>Under <a href="https://oregon.public.law/statutes/ors_166.015">ORS 166.015</a>, a <strong>riot</strong> occurs when six or more people engage in “tumultuous and violent conduct” that creates a “grave risk of causing public alarm.”</p><p>But here’s the problem:</p><ul>
<li>The term <strong>“tumultuous” is not defined</strong> in Oregon statute. It is left entirely to interpretation.</li>
<li>Police <strong>do not need proof of actual violence</strong>. The law allows a riot declaration based on perceived risk or potential to cause public alarm.</li>
<li>This means <strong>loud chanting, large crowds, or emotionally charged gatherings</strong> can be enough to trigger a riot declaration — even when nothing dangerous is actually happening.</li>
</ul>
<p>Once a riot is declared, officers are authorized to use force, including tear gas, rubber bullets, flashbangs, and mass detainment techniques. The <a href="https://www.aclu.org/know-your-rights/protesters-rights">ACLU of Oregon explains these risks clearly in their Protester Rights guide</a>.</p><h3 id="why-this-law-still-matters">Why This Law Still Matters</h3>
<p>This law was crafted to control protests, not protect public safety. Its roots lie in a time when authorities were actively working to silence racial justice movements and anti-war voices. Today, it remains a tool that can be used to chill public dissent.</p><p>If a protest is simply loud or makes someone uncomfortable, that alone can legally justify escalation under current law. That undermines the constitutional right to free assembly and creates a chilling effect, especially for movements that already face discrimination.</p><p>Major media outlets have also highlighted these problems. In 2020, <a href="https://www.opb.org/article/2020/08/28/riot-unlawful-assembly-law-oregon-police-racism/">OPB reported</a> that the laws governing riot declarations are vague and have roots in Oregon’s deeply racist past. As State Rep. Janelle Bynum explained, much of Oregon’s riot and crowd control statutes were developed during the 1960s and 1970s while protests for Black civil rights were occurring in Portland. OPB documented how police declared riots on 23 occasions between May 29 and August 27, often for incidents as minor as water bottles being thrown or spray paint being used.</p><p>Similarly, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/08/27/906729976/police-declare-portland-protests-a-riot-but-this-definition-could-be-rooted-in-r">NPR reported</a> that the legal definition of riot allows for wide discretion and disproportionately affects nonviolent protesters. Portland Police Deputy Chief Chris Davis admitted that deciding when enough “tumultuous” conduct has occurred to justify a riot declaration is ultimately subjective. Protesters like Folasade Ogunfiditimi described how quickly riots were declared, sometimes over minor or even trivial events, leading to unnecessary force being used indiscriminately against large crowds.</p><h3 id="examples-of-abuse">Examples of Abuse</h3>
<p><strong>June 2025, ICE Facility - “No Kings” Protest:</strong></p><ul>
<li>Portland police and federal officers declared a riot at the ICE facility around 6:30 p.m. despite limited incidents of violence. The declaration enabled rapid escalation, with tear gas and flashbangs deployed almost immediately against largely peaceful demonstrators. Critics argue this premature declaration unnecessarily escalated tensions and infringed on First Amendment rights.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2020 George Floyd Protests:</strong></p><ul>
<li>During months of protests in 2020, Portland police frequently declared riots after isolated incidents, such as minor property damage or confrontations involving small groups. Protesters were subjected to mass tear gas deployments, rubber bullets, and aggressive arrests even when large portions of the crowd remained peaceful.</li>
<li>Federal agents, often in unmarked uniforms, detained protesters in unmarked vehicles without clear identification. This sparked national outrage, with Governor Kate Brown and Mayor Ted Wheeler condemning the tactics as abuses of power and attacks on democratic rights.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2018 Patriot Prayer Rallies:</strong></p><ul>
<li>At several Patriot Prayer rallies and counter-protests, police were accused of declaring riots and deploying crowd-control munitions disproportionately against counter-protesters, raising concerns about selective enforcement and biased application of the riot law.</li>
</ul>
<p>Civil rights groups like the ACLU of Oregon have challenged these tactics in court, arguing that vague laws and aggressive enforcement tactics violate constitutional rights to free speech, assembly, and due process.</p><h3 id="what-needs-to-change">What Needs to Change</h3>
<p>We urgently need clarity, accountability, and civil liberties protection:</p><ol>
<li>Remove vague terms like <strong>“tumultuous”</strong> or define them with clear, objective standards.</li>
<li>Require documented evidence of violence or an imminent threat before force is authorized.</li>
<li>Establish independent oversight over riot declarations and crowd-control decisions.</li>
<li>Strengthen legal protections for peaceful protest and public assembly.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="we-deserve-better">We Deserve Better</h3>
<p>A functioning democracy requires more than the right to vote. It depends on the freedom to speak, gather, and demand change. Oregonians deserve a legal framework that protects those rights — not one that treats peaceful protest as a threat.</p><p><strong>It’s time to update Oregon’s riot law.</strong></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
